this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se - radio dotnet.
SC radio is brought to you by the I Triple E Computer Society,
I Triple E software magazine online at computer org slash softball.
this episode of se radio is brought to you by Braintree.
if you think that your payment system exists solely for the purpose of transferring money from your customers wall to yours, think again.
Braintree rethink payments, learn more at Braintree payments calm / se radio.
[Music]
hello. this is Matthew Farwell for software engineering radio, today's episode is about angular with Yakov fain.
Yakov is the co-author of the Amazon bestseller angular 2 development with typescript.
as well as a number of other technical books on programming.
Yakov works as a Software Architect the IT consultancy ferrata systems, a java champion.
he has taught multiple classes and workshops on web and java related technologies.
presented at the international conferences and published more than a thousand blog posts.
welcome to software engineering radio, Yakov. hi Matt, hello everybody.
today we're going to talk about angular, which is a JavaScript based web development framework.
we've had on software engineering radio some shows before on JavaScript.
notably to 4/8 acceleration Maya on JavaScript and equus script six.
and show to 30 with shubra car on nodejs.
but this time we're concentrating on front-end development.
okay, so let's start at the beginning.
Jakov, what is angular?
if you asked me this question two years ago, I'd say this is the framework for web development.
but now I'd rather say this as a platform for development of the front end of the web applications.
as well as mobile applications, as well as desktop applications.
so if this is a product developed by Google, and it was announced as a new version of super popular angularjs framework, which is version 1.
but actually it's a complete rewrite, it's a different framework.
and in my opinion it's much more powerful than what it used to be.
okay, so it's angular a framework or or a library?
it's definitely a framework, definitely.
what's the what's the difference?
the difference is that if you take a library, you can combine it with other libraries.
you can decide on the architecture of the application.
you can write everything say in pure JavaScript plus the library XYZ.
the library doesn't prescribe you to how to structure your applications, we framework does.
so frame-ups tell you how to do things, and you insert your code in playing by certain rules.
so in that regard angular is definitely a framework.
okay, I've heard it said that it's the Hollywood principle. don't call us, we'll call you.
would you agree with that?
the Hollywood principle is often mentioned in regards to particular aspect of the framework, and this would be dependency injection.
anger has this much right, so don't call me alcohol.
you mean means in my understanding that I'm not gonna be creating instances of the object whenever I want to.
I was a container, in this case angular being the container would do it for me and insert it into where I want.
okay, so in that regardless it is, but angular is much more than just dependency injection.
it has a bunch of modules, it has dependency injection, it has the router, super-powerful router.
it comes with the library called rxjs for reactive programming.
it comes with excellent tooling.
the recommended language for anger is typescript, which is the product of Microsoft.
also there is a module for server-side rendering, they integrate it with bundling tooling.
so it comes with the tools that allows you to create bundles that will be deployed on the web servers.
so in that regard you can say that.
angle framework comes with the batteries included.
okay, so why do we need a framework for JavaScript development?
why it's it's not a difficult question to answer, because not everybody is super smart.
not every developer who works on web applications is super smart.
who can pick and choose like a la carte kind of things, which library need or do any of them?
maybe I just will write everything in JavaScript.
we work in many cases in teams, and the skill level in any team, especially in the enterprise world, could be different.
there could be some experienced developers, some junior developers, and so.
so having a framework greatly simplifies the understanding of a particular application.
say I am a JavaScript developer who also knows angular, and to that matter any framework, and I join a team.
if you hired me knowing that I know this framework, you know that I will have easier times in getting on board.
in understanding how the application works, cause it it plays by certain rules and it belongs to certain structure.
so in that regard having a framework is beneficial for real-world enterprise development.
if you're a want one-man shop, and if you are very experienced developer, may be wrong need a framework.
would you describe angular is an opinionated framework?
definite actually, what is an opinionated framework?
well the framework that has an opinion how you're supposed to do things.
and in many cases angular plays certain restrictions as to how to do things.
for example, you want to implement an angular application which in most cases are so-called single page applications.
where a browser doesn't refer the entire page well, but only changes certain fragments on the page.
as the user navigate clicks on the links or buttons or so on.
there is a module called router, router tells you how you're supposed to navigate from point A to point B.
and in that regard there is certainly API that you have to stick to.
and it's not like you are free to do whatever you.
okay, what are the goals of angular then? what is the aim to help you with?
well apparently angular team would give you maybe more official proper answer.
the in my opinion, the goal of angular is to bring the common ground to a team that works on a web application.
the other goal would be to give them tools that will allow them,
the developers I mean, to easily solve tip issues.
that any application needs to solve, for example how do I never give the page as I said.
how do I build the project, how do I make sure that the user cannot click on a link until certain data is available?
how do i module arise the application, so my application is not a monolith, but it's cut into pieces.
so smaller pieces are loaded, and some pieces are loaded on demand.
so all that is given to you by angular framework.
so talking of components, what are the constituent parts of an angular application?
that's a good question, because angular comparing to angularjs is a complete switch in the architecture.
from being an MVC framework, Model View controller, to being component based framework.
so the application is a bunch of components, starting from the top level components, root component.
which may may have child component, children may have their own children, and so on.
so the application is a bunch of Legos, so to speak, components that can talk to each other, communicate with each other.
a component a can pass the data to component be.
a component B can send out events about some something that happens inside components.
can be brought together in a loosely coupled fashion, which is super important.
so yes, it's a component based framework, and the component is a piece of code with certain functionality.
typically a component consists of the code, recommended language is typescript.
even though you can write angular application in typescript, even in a couple of flavors of JavaScript.
such as atmosphere 5 atmosphere 6 7, or you can use a language called Dart, created by Google.
so the component consists of a file which has say class in typescript or script in type strip.
the other file could contain HTML, or you may decide to keep HTML inline.
the third oil could contain a CSS cascading stylesheets.
and what is or else is recommended to create testing, so you can create another file with extension spec spec that GS.
which would be say unit test or maybe entry and test.
but basically this group of files represent the component.
typical as these files are located in one directory.
so your project will consist of multiple directory sub directories, each directory will have a component.
it's not a visual component or is that?
yes, component is always something visual, it's something that has a UI.
think of it this way, you write a class in typescript.
and if you will add a decorator or annotation, in for example in Java we call these things annotations at component.
prepended to the class definition, and in there you define the template, you define CSS.
this is what makes a class a component.
without that at component annotations at the UI, it's not a component.
if you want to implement a piece of logic, then you just create a class and put any logics you want in there.
but this is not a component.
so component is always something with UI.
so angular does, angular help you with the other bits, the bits that aren't the visual stuff?
for instance he said that we have a class that we have to, if you have a service, if you have a common code between all of the components.
angler helps you in a way that it comes with an excellent tool which is called generator called angular CLI, command line interface.
that allows you to quickly generate either component or a directive or a class or a service.
by the way, we never gave a definition for this service, what is the service?
the service is also a class, but it contains only some business logic.
for example communication with the backend over some calculations, and services are injects it into components.
so if you write a component, then component has a constructor, and inside the in the constructor.
if you define an argument of type of certain service, for example product service or customer service.
which would bring you some data about product or customers.
in the component in the component constructor, you just define an argument of product service.
and angular is smart enough to understand, oh if you want product service, let me create an instance and inject it into this component.
when you say component, is that the same thing as a web component? it's not the same thing as a web component.
web component is a standard basically that consists of several things.
but you can think of it that you can think that angular components are very similar to what is planned for web components.
it is a piece of functionality with the UI.
let me put it this way, well encapsulated with well defined input and output.
and if you create a component in angular, you define in their so called selector.
say selector is product its class and notation in size annotation to define a selector product.
after that you can include this new tag in HTML, new tag being open angle bracket product closing in bread.
and this becomes in this in this sense it becomes a web component.
so when you look at the HTML of your application, you see all these angle brackets.
which some of them are HTML elements, while some of them represent angular components.
so how do I put an angular application together, how do I you build it up?
you mentioned dependency injection before, I did yes.
but the start became pretty painless so to speak.
a year ago many people complained that angular 2 is not easy to get into.
because it could come to a whole bunch of configuration files and two links.
and you write in typescript or deploy in JavaScript, and eat some kind of a tool to build.
yep, so angular team created an excellent tool called angular CLI, which is a code generator.
I already mentioned this, it can get you started real quickly.
you install it on your computer, and after that you get a comment and G.
and then you say ng new and name of the project on the command line.
limit and it takes like 30 seconds, and you get a new project directory, sub directories, and everything.
it it's a minimalistic application kind of hello world thing.
and you open it up either you open it up in your IDE, or you can just run another command from the command line.
and for example ng serve, this command instructs angular CLI build this app, create bundles out of it, and deploy it.
and you can open it up in the browser and it runs.
so in that regard it's very pretty easy to start.
if you want to open it in your IDE to see the structure and work like we always do.
you can pick up one of excellent IDs that are available.
for example, I'm using webstorm from JetBrains.
the other excellent idea is Visual Studio code, we just record, oh not to be confused with a little studio 2015.
visual record is a free open source ID.
then if you want you can install plugin for typescript and angular for sublime text for example.
support is just amazing, I mean people who just write JavaScript they can only dream of such support.
as we have in angular and typescript.
so you open up your IDE and you see a clean structure, folders, subfolders, SRC folder, a EPP folder.
as you keep adding new components, you get new folders, some number of configuration files.
and well-defined comments how to build a component, well sorry an application.
what is data binding?
data binding is about keeping things synchronized.
say you have a field on the UI, and you have a class variable in the typescript code.
and you want to make sure that if somebody is entering something in the UI control on the webpage, this value will jump right in that variable in typescript.
war if somebody modified the value of that variable, say you make a server question, the value value changed.
you want to immediately saw it on the UI.
so you can do this using binding.
you bind a variable in a class to control on the UI.
or you can bind say a button on the UI to a function that will handle that button click event.
and this is what the binding is.
is that two-way thing or it's not just simply one-way from the model to the to the page?
angular supports both way, by default way is one way, or they say unidirectional communication.
this is a big difference comparing to angularjs, where two-way binding was was a way to go, which caused some performance issues.
so in angular they decided to do things in unidirectional way.
so they are basically saying if you need to update something on the UI, just update a variable in your typescript class.
and since the variable is bound to the UI, the Y will be updated automatically.
but if you want to still use two-way binding in some cases, it may be beneficial.
for example, you have a simple form, and you want to bind every field on the form to certain variables up to a model.
you can use something called ng model, which is ng model with certain syntax which allow you to do binding in two ways.
but an angle celaya that i never mentioned, it comes as pretty convenient and powerful forms api.
so to be honest with you, I I can live pretty happily with one-way binding.
so it's not, how you do how you would handle things like validation for forms using validation of the form?
validation of the forms is handled using validation API, basically angular forms API.
comes with it comes with two API how to create a form itself.
one of them is so-called template driven, and the other one is so-called reactive API.
template driven is when you define the whole form inside the template, meaning like HTML like piece inside the annotation template.
where as reactive API is when you write actually code.
if you want to create a model that supports the form, you would create a new instance of the object model.
and you would add some field in there, but it will be in the code.
so to API for the form itself, and the the validation accordingly.
you can do validation using template API or using reactor API.
so you can write a function, for example say you want to validate the value of the email.
angle for comes with a prepackaged validator for email, or you want to require, or you want to do min max line.
these things are brief, they came out of the box.
but also you can create your custom validation, for example here in the United States we have social security number.
unique ID for every person in the country, it must have nine digits right.
so you can write those simple functions in there, you can put a regular expression that would make sure that it has nine digits.
and you it as you build the form, you can also attach one or more, actually zero or more validators to every form control.
and the the thing will work automatically.
also forms API supports asynchronous validation, so you can do validation server for example, it also works pretty well that work.
does it do an HTTP call to the server to to validate?
let me put it more generically, it makes a call to a service that you will write.
cameraman service, services just a class.
so you can say here's the class which has a whole bunch of different filtration methods.
and inside these methods you can, if you want, make HTTP calls and asynchronously as the data comes back, validating on the server side.
your you will get either okay like the value is valid or not okay. and you knew that you subscribe for the changes.
actually we never mentioned, you never touch the subject of reactive programming of rxjs.
but even in in forms you can subscribe to changes, like form was not valid, now it is valid, or the validation request comes back.
so it's super powerful.
okay, we own software engineering radio, we've had two or three shows on reactive programming.
in notably two six seven year in Halle reactive spring, and two four nine the von Vernon on reactive programming with actors.
but could you describe how reactive programming fits in with angular?
definitely, definitely, I do reactive programming in two languages.
I'm using our X Java to for Java, and I'm using rxjs 5 which is bundled with angular.
reactive programming in angular is used with the support of the library that.
is called rxjs.
rxjs 5 specifically is packaged with angular, and it's built on the same principles as any reaction except library is observable.
is it something that pushes data, observer is a class as an object or a functions, it knows what to do is the data when it arrives.
a bunch of operators that can handle the data in route so to speak.
so as a day that comes from observable to the subscriber to this stream, you can chain a bunch of operators in there and processes.
for example filter map and many other things, like about maybe a hundreds of operators or so.
so in angular in multiple occasions they already use, and they give you these eggs access to these observable streams.
for example, when you move using router from point A to point B, in many cases you need to pass the data as you are moving along.
for example, you're looking at the screen with product ID, there is a list of products.
and you want to go to another area we do another component, it shows product detail product itself.
or which product, you need to pass an ID right.
so in the router you can subscribe to changing IDs that are giving from component ly to component B using the router.
are we talking about the two bits of a page, the two sides for page?
yes yes, two components which can be sitting on the same page like master detail kind of thing.
implementation why master component and shows the list of products, you click on it initially it goes.
and shows on the right the detail about this component, but that's a separate component in of itself.
detail component as a stream of the selected, as you select different product the stream gives you different IDs.
and they mention already in the forms he also use subscription to observables.
HTTP requests is done using the same paradigm.
when you make an HTTP request you're getting back not a promise as it used to be negligees, but you subscribe to an observable.
even though the HTTP request is typically one thing one item, you still subscribe.
you may have you may use WebSocket and subscribe to incoming data this way as well.
so in many places it is being used, plus you can write your own services that are wrappers for rxjs library.
and you can implement any rx flows as you want.
so an HTTP request just to clarify, an HTTP request is done via our X as an observable.
and then eventually you will get a a response back right.
I should use an asynchronous operation.
so there is an HTTP object inside that comes with angular.
and obviously they define these standard methods in their get put post delete and so on.
each of these methods returns and observable, when you see that in the dock, it means that you can subscribe to it.
okay, and moreover it gives you a power that you may not find in other places.
for example, let's say you have a you make an HTTP request and you are holding a mobile phone in a slow connection area.
what happened is the user becomes annoyed because the request is not coming back for five seconds.
so he enters something else, and he makes another request.
for example, I wanted to check the price on the IBM in stock market, now let me know, no you didn't come back, let me check the apples price.
so what happens with the first request, it's never come back, it will come back eventually.
and it will clog your poor bandwidth, and whenever it comes back using the operators.
in particular I'm referring to switch map operator in rx, you can easily kill the unfinished request in one line.
so it's X, so it cancels the request, it killed the drain.
so this this this brings us onto an interesting question, am i forced to use rxjs or can I replace it with another?
you're saying that Angela gives me a framework and makes a lot of decisions for me.
could I replace rxjs with another libraries such as bacon?
no, you can't do this, basically our exists is the dependency of angular.
I mean obviously you can do anything you want, if you if your goal is to kill this framework and do something else.
but it would be a very difficult job, and I don't see a reason to do this.
for example, you have an HTTP object that come to this angular, underneath it's assumed that you will be subscribing to to it using rx.
can you make a surgery somehow, maybe if you are Hector you me, but why explain why I don't see reason why doing this.
one of the questions that came to mind is if you if you didn't want to use a library which was specifically written for angular.
for instance jQuery UI, or if you wanted to use XML wrath on Jason, an XML library rather than JSON library.
are there are there points at which you can plug in new functionality?
yes, but it's different, and what you asked before is can you rip our x-rays from angular and put something else inside, that's one thing.
but if you are asking can I use third-party JavaScript library which are tons of you is angular?
the answer is yes, you can add even though it's not needed.
but say you you're a fan of jQuery UI, and even though angular has its own library called angular material 2.
you may say I don't want to use it, I want to use jQuery UI, I am pretty comfortable, or I know a particular component that I love.
yes, you can do this, you can add jQuery UI as a dependency.
and you will install all the pendants in your project, like very well will be installed inside the node modules library where everything else is.
and there are a couple of cases how do you work with external libraries.
one of them, you can find so-called typescript definition file, if you want to have full ad support for something written in JavaScript with stipes.
or you can just declare this variable, for example if you want to add jQuery.
you know that jQuery creates a global object inside the browser right, they query Horace's that dollar.
you can declare this variable and say I'm gonna get it there when the application will run.
there will be something known as a dollar, and you can use the API if you'll do it a simple way like I just said.
by declaring a variable you will not get support of IDs.
on the other hand, since typescript is a typed language, and good people out there from the community created typed nation for jQuery.
for example, and you can download it, and then you will get full support for the API as you use jQuery inside angular.
again it's not recommended using jQuery, but there are other libraries.
for example d3, people use it for charting, and they want to use it with angular same procedure.
users want a simple way to pay, you want an easy integration.
Braintree allows you to accept nearly any payment type from almost any device with just one integration.
it's flexible to your systems needs and supports most programming languages.
and when your checkout is simpler and faster, you're going to have happier customers.
that's what we call a win-win, learn more at Braintree payments comm /se radio.
so what doesn't angular do, it has this defined way that it wants you to work.
what doesn't take cover?
what are the what are the pain points with angular?
I don't know of any specific pain points, but there is there are some areas that angular delegates mmm things too.
one of the smart decision when they decide designed angler was to make a renderer SEP a separate piece, the piece it renders the UI.
that open up the opportunity for third party companies to replace HTML as a renderer as a language for rendering with something else.
for example, there is a library called native script.
native script is a library for mobile development, and it allows they give you their own set of tags.
that you can use in angular templates, and these tags are internally in that library are mapped to native components on iOS or Android.
so if you decide to use angular for mobile development, I'm talking about not a hybrid development.
where the mobile phone will run the some web view or web browser internally, and then Europe.
I'm talking about native rendering of native components of ios and android, you can use that native script library and their tags.
instead of using divs or whatever input fields in HTML, you will use you will be using zere tags, and they will compile it into native libraries.
so this is I would say this is a delegation of something that is not implemented in angular 2 somewhere else.
or there is UI library, you can use standard UI, you can use you Ivers bootstrap if you want from Twitter.
or angular team currently is developing a UI library called angular material 2.
for now as of today it feels like 25 UI controls, very well done, high quality control.
but 25 control is not enough for a real application.
so there are third-party libraries, for example we use in our company we use Prime and G prime ng.
is noble source library which has 70 plus UI controls.
so we use a mix of angular material to controls and primary.
so there are areas that are it could be complemented, but it's not developed by angular team so to speak.
is angular open source?
angler is open source, it's MIT license yes.
and where did it come from, who develops angular?
Google has the team specifically designated angular team who works early for two years from this framework.
and they have within that team they have dedicated groups.
for example one of them is working on angular material to, the other group is working on angular CLI and so on.
but it's a it's a Google driven framework.
okay, and they have excellent collaboration with Microsoft, two years ago when they started developing English.
- what was used to call angle, - now it's already angular 4.
they plant to you to create a special language for it for the framework called earth script.
and then they looked at typescript, and they contacted Microsoft asking guys if you will add certain things to your language, we will be happily using typescript.
Microsoft agreed, and there is an excellent collaboration in that regard between Google Microsoft.
typescript is booming now, I think that angular contributes a lot to the popularity of typescript.
I believe in if you will check latest Stack Overflow or developer service.
and so typescript is one of the most, I mean it's jumped right into like 10 most popular English and loved language.
and so on so typescript benefits and angular benefits, like Stroupe is an excellent language.
and and well it was created by the same creator who created c-sharp right, so probably they know how to create languages.
so I really like it, just briefly could you explain what typescript is.
typescript is a superset of JavaScript.
by saying superset in a simplistic way, I can explain that if you have a file written in JavaScript Maine dot Jas.
with some script if you will just rename it to Maine dot T s GS is extension type strip, then it's a valid typescript code already.
you didn't change a thing yet, but type scripts introduce types, so you can declare variables with types.
first of all, typescript is based on the JavaScript standards, it's built on them, and it adds certain new things.
so you can declare types, but and they don't force you to declare types.
you can keep just using variables without declaring them, and typescript is smart enough to figure out what is the time that you want.
on the other hand, you can upfront declare types, and then you'll get the whole power of tooling and IDE support and everything.
also they yet think that JavaScript don't doesn't have, me being a Java developer for me it's very easy to learn.
for example they have interfaces in typescript which don't exist in Java.
interfaces are very similar to what we use in Java, or they have so-called generics.
we have them in Java, and they have them in typescript.
so they use async/await already in the language.
so they play by the rules, meaning that they look in the tc39 standards what's going on with the next new script language.
and they implement it sooner or they expand it.
but the fact that you write in the typescript means that you need to transpile it or compile it into javascript.
because browsers don't support transcriptions a year, they are not planning to.
so you add an extra step of compilation and types of campus compiler.
also ty trip has excellent idea support, so they have a special language service and with a bunch of plugins that work the same in any IDE.
so it helps you a lot know in development, it makes develop at much more productive.
why did angular choose typescript rather than just going for straight JavaScript?
again productivity, productivity matters.
I can tell you based, I can tell the experience from our camp many years ago.
we used to use actually we still use it, but we started many years ago a project using a super popular bags and framework called Adobe flex.
I don't know if you remember that X, it was excellent framework, excellent web development framework.
but is required for each player as a runtime, which is out of fashion for many years as everybody knows.
we had ton of code written in Flex framework, and we started to look into JavaScript world.
how do we move pieces of flex code into JavaScript.
and we have excellent developers, any developers he started to give them take this piece and rewrite it in JavaScript.
and we know this immediate drop in productivity when people started write in JavaScript again.
they are smart guys, that whatever you could do in Flex in one day, in JavaScript you would need to do in four or five days.
and it in typescript we see that it's much closer to what we saw before in strong or strict languages.
so you you're saying you prefer typescript because it's it's more productive and and more predictable.
and to like is a lot more a lot better than with JavaScript.
you spoke earlier on about testing, about using the spec Jas, how do we do automated testing with angular?
angle comes with a couple of frameworks already.
remember I told you in the beginning you use angular CLI, it generates your project which includes support for unit testing and for end-to-end testing.
and you are automatically install through the project that is this installed with Jasmine framework, which is super popular in JavaScript world.
so that the framework for unit testing that is supported by default by angular.
angle has some API on top of it, but by default they support J and Jasmine, and they also support mocha framework for unit testing.
for end-to-end testing, on sometimes sometimes and people call it functional testing, when the entire application is emulated.
like as if users are clicking through the buttons and going through the menus.
for that it comes with protractor framework, also open source, but it's from Google's.
so the frameworks are there,
and also the Neo generated project comes pre-configured a karma test runner.
so you can run the test from the command line, karma is again very popular, it's a whole bunch of plugins for different browsers.
so since you can run tests using karma command line command, command you can implement it in your build process.
so when you run builds or deployments, you put in the in the in the script this one extra line karma, and which will start your tests.
so this is how you automate your testings.
and what can we test, you can test any piece of functionality.
for example in your test you can test a function, you can take this a class.
but specifically for angular there are a certain certain members of the framework that require testing, such as router.
ok, we want to test the router, what if I want to pour water place a to place B.
router actively uses this location or address bar of the browser.
so it tries to match whatever you see in the location to whatever was configured there out in the code.
so it checks that it works nicely.
now when you create a component in the angular framework, and the component get data from somewhere and populate the variable.
and it shows on the UI using binding, and all this happens magically, how can you test that?
now you want to write a test that will manually create an instance of a component.
and manual you want to do something that will force the UI to change, so that API is are there.
or you want to do write a unit test for services, service makes a request to the server side using HTTP for example.
but in unit just must be fast, we don't want to remember we don't want our test to fail just because somebody else's server is done.
so there are mocks for all these HTTP requests, so we can create mocks and make sure our test works.
so these are specific things for angular.
can you simulate events such as the user clicking on a button or the user moving the mouse?
of course you can see economy late an event that's correct.
moreover, we never touched one thing which is the change detection.
how angular knows that UI has to be updated refreshed, that's something some value changed, and it needs to be pushed to the UI.
this is a area of major improvement comparing to angularjs.
in angularjs a developer was responsible for for saying oh I believe that now is the right moment to update the UI.
in angular there is the use special library called zone GS that is monitoring any asynchronous calls that can be originated from your app.
and they they group them together and understand that yo you made two three asynchronous calls, did they come back?
for example you click on the button, you call set timeout, you made HTTP requests one or two.
so this zone J's understand that you created a bunch of asynchronous calls, and now they came back.
and it now it automatically will push the changes to the UI.
so when you write tests unit tests, you can force this change detection from your tests to see how things will work in the real world.
can we test the correct HTML is produced?
yes, you can, when you when I mentioned that you can test components, you would be manually creating an instance of new class which represents a component.
but component is a class plus template, so you will create many line instance of the component.
you will get a reference to this object in memories of Houston sheet, but also you will get a reference to the dome element that angular would create for you.
because component needs to be represented eventually as a domain.
so you would create an instance of this component in a special way, get two references.
one to the instance of the class in memory, and the other to the instance of the dome element.
then on the class you will set the variable say customer name to Mary, and then you initiate change detection.
and then you will write a test checking do I have an h1 element with the value is innerhtml as Mary.
so you can definitely test that, you achieve you assign the variable in the class in the object, and then you see the same value in the Dom.
so you can test it.
okay, what just quickly, what is the Tom document object model right?
so it's basically when you look at the page in the browser, behind the page there is like a tree of elements.
so if you have a page with a button and an anchor tag a link, behind the scenes you'll have a tree of bridges represent your page.
so anytime you create the browser renders the page behind them, there is a Dom tree or Dom object.
okay, I'd like to move on to performance now.
what are the major performance is using a JavaScript or a web application?
in angularjs in older version of angular there were performance problem in rendering.
and many in many occasions these problem were caused by two-way bindings that is used under the hood magically everywhere.
and now change detection mechanism, it does one single path through the component tree.
for example, you means I made a change in the UI in in a grandchild component.
this change detection mechanisms will traverse your tree of components from top to bottom only one time.
there is no circle dependency, nothing comparing to what was there before.
so in that regard UI is much faster.
second there are easy ways to modularize an application,
your application can have a landing page which is very light, and it will be rendered pretty fast.
and this would give the user feeling, actually it's a perceived performance right.
so maybe it's not actual performance in front, but the user will be very happy because boom the landing page is right there.
and in the background other modules will be loaded.
so when users will click on the button, the module rebuild either will be loaded on demand or or it could be pre-loaded.
the other thing is the when the bundles are created there is a process called tree shaking.
under the hood of epic comes with it, and it's removed so color is not used.
so a small application, the size of the small application is that you deploy is like around a hundred kilobytes, which is rather small.
I mean this includes the framework, ok your code is of small app plus a frame.
and you mentioned earlier on server-side page rendering, could you explain what that is and how angular does it?
and basically the reason there was an effort which initially which.
started as the is a community effort to create something called angular Universal.
the idea was to pre render the page, to pre create it on the server.
so I mean first of all a page will downloading of the page would be faster if it's ready.
and second it would be much more friendlier in terms of search engine optimization.
so this was an effort, it was community driven.
and now angle decided to include it as a part of framework, and I'm not exactly sure about the scheduling, but I believe it's already a part of thing dollar.
so if you want you can use angular Universal to pre render pages on the server.
say ok, and just quickly moving on to security.
what are the main issues in browser security, and what are the types of exploits that can be carried out?
if you don't think about security when you're developing your application.
angular doesn't introduce any new threads or any additional provisions in terms of security, not that I know of actually no.
there is one, there is so called sunny sanitizer which they prevent from when.
you a rendering images they prevent from entering malicious code.
other than that angular is as secure or as insecure as any other web application.
so there is nothing additional that you that is introduced by angular.
in angular typically what you would do, you would create a service for a cessation of syndication, you would invoke it.
and based on that you can arrange navigation, moreover we can allow you to click on this link if you are a manager or admin.
and not click on the link if you're not admit.
also when we work in dev mode and go account with the dev server, actually under the hood is a web pack their server.
so the way you work is you run the build in a special mode, so it's built in memory and you keep working.
you could keep making changes in the code, and it sort of immediately rerender on the page.
and you run it on certain port, for example 4200.
on the other hand, you may have a server written in some other technology running in port 8080.
that's all, it's the rest servers that would she do data.
so we have a situation, how do you deal with the same origin problem?
so you want to use this local and web server, you make requests to the server and port 4215.
but your applications that load it needs to make requests for data to the server that runs from 8080.
so you kind of follow violate the same origin policy.
so in angular they allow you to create so-called proxy file.
and you can see that whenever you see in the API in the URL of the request a check request say slash API.
then redirect it to a server running on port 8080.
it's also very easy to be done in English.
so let me see if I if I've got that, angular doesn't necessarily apart from the sanitization like you say.
it doesn't necessarily help you with authentication, or there's no there's nothing built-in to help you with authentication or any other any of the other exploits that you could have.
actually said that it here's the class for Sunnis and it's sanitization for the images, but other than that and I don't know about any specific provisions right.
okay, so imagine I have an existing complex such application with which is just using javascript.
I want to move towards angular T for this application.
do I need to do all at once or can I do it piece by piece?
there is basically angular is meant for creating of single page applications.
so it's the best fit is to create an app and it loaded as a main application and then use it.
but if you want to use it in pieces, you can still do this.
you can create maybe a library using angular, you can publish it as a package as a module as an angular module.
it will be compiled into a module.
and if you want to use it, if your main application supports working with modules, then you can load it.
but to be honest with you, I wouldn't go this route.
if I want to if I had an application in JavaScript, I would probably go all the way around.
I would create a maybe a shell or a main page in angular, and then I would bring gradually or in one shot we hold the rest of the code.
okay right, so thank you for talking to us, yeah cough. is there anything else I should have asked you?
probably you should have asked me if angular is one of the best solution in the market today or not. I would say that.
for the front-end development angle will have the same impact as for example a Spring Framework had in the Java world.
it is a large framework, it can be used in many areas.
it is a good fit when you had have an enterprise team with different skill level.
it has everything that she needs.
so when the new person comes into the project, if he knows angular and worked somewhere else, so he pretty much can start working pretty fast.
in many cases in community they start these flaming words such as what is better angular or react.
for example, in general it's a wrong approach, because angular is the framework while react is a library.
but I can just say that.
if you have, I already mentioned this in the beginning, if you have a group of one or more people with super skills.
then you can go with library, but otherwise I would recommend using angular.
how can listeners find out more about angular?
the listeners can go to angular dot IO, and there is a link to the documentation, there's a plenty of documentation on over there.
there are plenty of books written on angular, including yours, including ours, it's not me, it's me and my colleague.
then chance of blog, also I would recommend watching one particular conference Google run conference twice a year called ng-conf.
typically there is a lots of high quality there are lots of high quality presentation and talk over there.
and they are literally next day available on YouTube.
so I would recommend watching the air, and Stack Overflow works pretty nicely, it's very active.
as a matter of fact, I believe that it's about a million people today who are already using mmm angular with typescript.
so the community is huge, and stack overflow will help you pretty fast.
okay, so thank you for joining us, yeah cough.
where can people find out more about you and your books?
well I have a blog which is myname calm, yak of feigned calm, i have twitter obviously.
why fame is the same handle on the stack overflow, the same, where else on github.
and I'm pretty pleased and happy with the fact that and we published the code samples for the book on github.
and this project was called sample has almost 300 stars, to me is the best best appreciation.
I think that we did a good job with that book, and we keep updating that github site.
so if you don't want to buy a book for whatever reason, then go and get hub and download many many examples that we created. we'll link to those in the show notes.
sorry, this is Matthew Farwell for software engineering radio, thank you for listening. thank you.
thanks for listening to se Radio, an educational program brought to you by Triple E software magazine.
for more about the podcast including other episodes visit our website at se - radio net.
to provide feedback you can comment on each episode on the website, or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through our slack channel at SC radio slack calm.
you can also email us at team @ SC - radio net.
this and all other episodes of SU radio is licensed under Creative Commons license 2.5. thanks for listening.